[A Guide to the Blacksburg Woman's Club Records 1907-1972
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
Blacksburg Woman's Club Records 1907-1972
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
Ms63-002
8 containers; 7 cu. ft.
Records of the Blacksburg Woman's Club. Includes club correspondence, minutes, financial records, scrapbooks and printed material.
Donor
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
The Blacksburg Woman's Club deposited many of its records in Newman Library in 1962; those materials were donated to the library the following year. Upon dissolution of the club in 1970, the club donated the remainder of its records. Additional materials were donated by the club's last president in 1972, and a 1941/1942 scrapbook was donated in 1990.
Biographical/Historical Information
Arising from a desire to improve the cultural and environmental aspects of life in the Blacksburg area, the Woman's Civic Betterment Club was founded in 1907. Led by its first president, Mrs. R. H. Hudnall, the organization became affiliated with the Virginia Federation of Women's Clubs in 1912 and was renamed the Blacksburg Woman's Club in 1914. Throughout the next several decades, the club was involved in a number of local civic improvement projects, involving community beautification, public health, civil defense, charity and cultural programs. The Blacksburg Garden Club was originally a committee within the Blacksburg Woman's Club before voting to form an independent organization in 1930. Another offshoot organization, The Blacksburg Junior Woman's Club, was created in 1935 and continues to be active today (2003). The club disbanded in 1970
Scope and Content Information
This collection contains the records of the Blacksburg Woman's Club. The collection includes the club's correspondence; official minutes of both the general club and executive committee meetings; and financial records. The core of the collection is found in a large set of scrapbooks, ranging from the 1930s to 1970s, which include materials from all facets of the club's activities. Also contained in the collection are printed materials of both the Blacksburg Woman's Club and the Virginia Federation of Women's Clubs. A small collection of photos and ephemera completes the collection. Scattered throughout the collection are materials relating to the Blacksburg Junior Woman's Club.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged in the following series:
I. Correspondence, 1953-1970. This series contains a small set of correspondence, most of which is from the club's final few years and was apparently overlooked during the compilation of scrapbooks. Arranged chronologically.
II. Minutes, 1907-1970. In addition to the minutes of the general club meetings, this series also contains minutes of the executive committee meetings. Arranged by type, then chronologically.
III. Financial Records, 1914-1970. The club's financial records include the treasurers' books and reports, as well as documentation such as check stubs, deposit slips and receipts, most of which are from the few years immediately preceding the club's dissolution. Arranged by type, then chronologically.
IV. Scrapbooks, 1936-1968. By far the most extensive of the series, the scrapbooks comprise the core of the collection. Covering 30 years of the club's history, the scrapbooks contain a large variety of materials, including correspondence, memorabilia, minutes, calendars, rosters, newspaper clippings and other printed materials relating to both the Blacksburg Woman's Club and the Virginia Federation of Women's Clubs. Arranged chronologically.
V. Club Activities, 1937-1970. This small series contains various histories of the club, together with materials (mostly printed matter) relating to various activities, specifically the 1952 "Get Out the Vote" campaign. Arranged by type, then chronologically.
VI. Printed Materials, 1917-1970. Included in the printed materials are the club's newsletters and yearbooks, as well as a history and a cookbook published by the club. The series also contains a few publications of the Virginia Federation of Women's Clubs and a few newspaper clippings. Arranged by format, then chronologically, with local publications preceding those of the statewide organization.
VII. General Materials, 1964-1968. This small series contains a few photos of club members and some assorted ephemera. Arranged by type.
Contents List
- SERIES I. CORRESPONDENCE 1953-1970
  - Correspondence 1953-1970, n.d. (Box-folder 1-1)
- SERIES II. MINUTES 1907-1970
  - General meeting minutes
    - 1907-1921 (Box-folder 1-2)
    - 1921-1938 (Box-folder 1-3)
    - 1938-1948 (Box-folder 1-4)
    - 1949-1950 (Box-folder 1-5)
    - 1951-1953 (Box-folder 1-6)
    - 1954-1956 (Box-folder 1-7)
    - 1957-1965 (Box-folder 1-8)
    - 1966-1970 (Box-folder 1-9)
  - Executive Committee minutes
    - 1940-1944 (Box-folder 2-1)
    - 1946-1956 (Box-folder 2-2)
    - 1956-1964 (Box-folder 2-3)
    - 1964-1970 (Box-folder 2-4)
- SERIES III. FINANCIAL RECORDS 1914-1970
  - Treasurer's books 1917-1951, [3 items] (Box-folder 2-5)
  - Treasurer's reports 1936-1970 (Box-folder 2-6)
  - Bank account books 1914-1969, [3 items] (Box-folder 2-7)
  - Check stubs 1921-1970 (Box-folder 2-8)
  - Checks 1966-1970 (Box-folder 2-9)
  - Deposit slips 1966-1970 (Box-folder 2-10)
  - Bank statements 1966-1970 (Box-folder 2-11)
  - Receipts and other financial records
    - 1942-1968 (Box-folder 2-12)
    - 1969-1970, n.d. (Box-folder 2-13)
- SERIES IV. SCRAPBOOKS 1936-1968
  - Scrapbooks
    - 1936/1937 (Box-folder 3-1)
    - 1936/1937 (Box-folder 3-1)
    - 1938/1939 (Box-folder 3-2)
    - 1940/1941 (Box-folder 3-3)
    - 1941/1942 (Box-folder 3-4)
    - 1942/1943 (Box-folder 3-5)
    - 1945/1946 (Box-folder 3-6)
    - 1946/1947 (Box-folder 4-1)
    - 1947/1948 (Box-folder 4-2 (2 folders))
    - 1948/1949 (Box-folder 4-3 (2 folders))
    - 1949/1950 (Box-folder 4-4 (3 folders))
    - 1950/1951 (Box-folder 5-1 (2 folders))
    - 1951/1952 (Box-folder 4-2 (3 folders))
    - 1953/1954 (Box-folder 6-1)
    - 1954/1955 (Box-folder 6-2)
    - 1955/1956 (Box-folder 6-3)
    - 1956/1957 (Box-folder 6-4)
    - Golden anniversary 1957 (Box-folder 6-5)
    - 1957/1958 (Box-folder 6-6)
    - 1958/1959 (Box-folder 6-7)
    - 1959/1960 (Box-folder 6-8)
    - 1960/1961 (Box-folder 7-1)
    - 1961/1962 (Box-folder 7-2)
    - 1962-1963 (Box-folder 7-3)
    - 1963/1964 (Box-folder 7-4)
    - 1964/1965 (Box-folder 7-5)
    - 1965-1966 (Box-folder 7-6)
    - 1966/1967 (Box-folder 7-7)
    - 1967/1968 (Box-folder 7-8)
- SERIES V. CLUB ACTIVITIES 1937-1970
  - Club histories 1937-1969 (Box-folder 8-1)
  - "Get Out the Vote" campaign 1952 (Box-folder 8-2)
  - Committee and presidential reports 1952-1970 (Box-folder 8-3)
  - Programs, brochures and press releases 1957-1970 (Box-folder 8-4)
- SERIES VI. PRINTED MATERIALS 1917-1970
  - Newsletters
    - 1960-1965 (Box-folder 8-5)
    - 1966-1970 (Box-folder 8-6)
  - Yearbooks 1919-1970 (Box-folder 8-7)
  - Blacksburg Woman's Club History 1938 (Box-folder 8-8)
  - My Stove and I[cookbook] 1952? (Box-folder 8-9)
  - "Discovering Blacksburg" 1965-1968 (Box-folder 8-10)
  - Virginia Federation of Women's Clubs yearbooks 1917-1951, [2 items] (Box-folder 8-11)
  - The Virginia Club Woman 1963-1970, [8 items] (Box-folder 8-12)
  - Newspaper clippings 1938-1948 (Box-folder 8-13)
- SERIES VII. GENERAL MATERIALS 1917-1970
  - Photos and ephemera 1964-1968, n.d. (Box-folder 8-14)